<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A cloud of vvitnesses: with whom I also appear to bear testimony, that Christ Jesus is the word of God, and not the Bible which is called the Scriptures. For which the word the prophets, apostles, and servants of the Lord, obeying, and bearing their testimony thereunto, have suffered by all generations of men, cruel mockings, stripes, bonds, and imprisonments, by the Egyptians, Philistians, Babylonians, Caldeans, idolaters, back-sliders, Roman Papists, and in generall, the heathen that know not Christ Jesus to be the word of the Lord. ... / Written by him, who is known by the name of Henry Clark.</title>
            <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E872_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865688</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79860)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E872[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A cloud of vvitnesses: with whom I also appear to bear testimony, that Christ Jesus is the word of God, and not the Bible which is called the Scriptures. For which the word the prophets, apostles, and servants of the Lord, obeying, and bearing their testimony thereunto, have suffered by all generations of men, cruel mockings, stripes, bonds, and imprisonments, by the Egyptians, Philistians, Babylonians, Caldeans, idolaters, back-sliders, Roman Papists, and in generall, the heathen that know not Christ Jesus to be the word of the Lord. ... / Written by him, who is known by the name of Henry Clark.</title>
                  <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Black spread-Eagle, neer the vvest end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march. 29.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Word of God (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CLOVD OF VVITNESSES: With whom I alſo appear to bear Teſtimony, That Chriſt Jeſus is the Word of God, and not the Bible which is called the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>For which Word the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Servants of the Lord, obeying, and bearing their Teſtimony there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, have ſuffered by all Generations of men, cruel Mockings, Stripes, Bonds and Impriſonments, by the <hi>Egytians, Philiſtians, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians, Caldeans, Idolaters, Back-ſliders, Roman Papists,</hi> and in generall, the <hi>Heathen,</hi> that know not Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to be the Word of the Lord.</p>
            <q>
               <p>For we are as Strangers before thee, and Sojourners, as were all our Fathers, our dayes of the earth are as a ſhadow, and there is none abiding on the earth; they wandered about in ſheep-skins, and goat-skins, they wandered in deſerts, and upon mountains, and being deſtitute, lay in dens and caves of the earth, and obtained a good report through faith, <bibl>1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37, 38, 39.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Do not rich men oppreſs you, and draw you before Judgment-ſeats? <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.6. and the princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over you, &amp; they that are great exerciſe authority upon you, <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>He is a choſen veſſel unto me, to bear my Name before the Gentiles and Kings, and the Children of Iſrael, and I will ſhew him how great things he muſt ſuffer for my Names ſake: Be of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <hi>Paul,</hi> for thou haſt teſtified of me in Jeruſalem, ſo muſt thou bear witneſs alſo at Rome: and certain of the Jews banded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, more then fourty men, and bound themſelves with an oath, and lay in wait for him, ſaying, that they would neither eat nor drink, till they had killed <hi>Paul,</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15, 16, &amp; 23.11, 12. &amp; 21.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Written by him, who is known by the Name of <hi>Henry Clark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> Giles Calvert, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the Black ſpread-Eagle, neer the VVest end of</hi> Pauls, 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117937:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117937:2"/>
            <head>A CLOVD OF VVITNESSES, With whom I alſo appear to bear Tiſtimony, That Chriſt Jeſus is the Word of God, and not the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which is called the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHen Chriſt ſaid to the Jews, <hi>Search the Scripture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.46, 47.</note> he did not ſay, that they are the Word of the Lord, as it is written in a Chapter, and a Verſe: but told them, <hi>That they think in them,</hi> that teſtifie of him, <hi>to have E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life:</hi> but life was not in them to be had, but in the Son,<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. <hi>John</hi> 12.36.</note> 
               <hi>for he that hath the Son, hath lift:</hi> and unto him they would not come <hi>that they might have eternall life,</hi> who is the light and life of men, which light they would not own nor believe in: Nor did they believe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Writings, which Chriſt called the Scriptures, and bad them ſearch, for ſaid he, <hi>Had ye beleeved</hi> Moſes, <hi>ye would have beleeved me, for he wrote of me;</hi> but ſaid Chriſt, <hi>If ye beleeve not his writings, how ſhall ye beleeve my words?</hi> Now here it is plainly ſeen, that, that part of the Scripture which Chriſt bad the Jews to ſearch, he called them, <hi>Moſes</hi> Writings;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.42. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.35.40</note> and the other part (as <hi>Stephen</hi> was bearing his Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, and againſt the Temple made with hands) he called it the Book of the Prophets: he did not ſay, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117937:3"/> unto the Word of the Lord, as the Prieſts of England do, that preach for hire, as it is written in a Chapter and a Verſe, but ſaid, <hi>As it is written in the Book of the Prophets:</hi> And when the Lawyer ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt which was the greateſt Commandment in the Law, when Chriſt had told him, he ſaid, <hi>On theſe two Commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets.</hi> And likewiſe after his reſurrection, and being preſent with his Apoſtles, he ſaid unto them, <hi>Theſe are the words which I ſpake unto you, while I was with you, that all things muſt be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled which were written</hi> (he did not ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.44.</note> in the Word of God) <hi>in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and in the Prophets, and in the Pſalms concerning me.</hi> So it is ſaid likewiſe of <hi>Paul,</hi> that to the Jews which came to his lodging, he expounded and teſtified the Kingdom of God, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them concerning Jeſus, both out of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and out of the Prophets: ſo that it doth plainly appear, that thoſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which were then written, were called by Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Moſes VVritings, Moſes Law,</hi> and the <hi>Book of the Prophets, the Prophets, and the Pſalms,</hi> (and not the Word of the Lord) all which teſtifie of Chriſt. So likewiſe thoſe that are written ſince them are called a <hi>Declaration;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Luke</hi> ſaid, <hi>Foraſmuch as many have taken in hand to ſet forth in order d Declaration of thoſe things which are moſt ſurely beleeved amongſt us, which from the beginning were eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and Miniſters of the VVord: it ſeemed good to me alſo, having a perfect underſtanding of all things from the very firſt, to write unto thee in order, moſt excellent</hi> Theophilus: And <hi>Luke</hi> he writes in order his <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Iohn,</hi> his birth and parentage, and of his going out to preach and baptize; and likewiſe of the birth and diſcent of Chriſt, and of his Parents, and of the manner of his going out to preach, and the calling of his dlſciples, and ſending them out to preach likewiſe; and of his works and miracles, travells, doctrine, ſufferings, death and reſurrection. And <hi>Matthew,</hi> and <hi>Mark,</hi> they wrote their <hi>Declaration</hi> of what they were eye witneſſes of. And <hi>Iohn</hi> he writ his Teſtimony of Jeſus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.30. &amp; <hi>chap.</hi> 21.24, 25.</note> what he was, and ſaid, and did, and alſo of his death and reſurrection, which Teſtimony was but a part of what he ſaw and knew; for ſaid he, <hi>Many other ſignes Ieſus did in the preſence of his diſciples, which are not written in this Book;</hi> and there were many other things which Ieſus did, which if they ſhould be be written every one, I ſuppoſe that even the world it ſelf could not contain the Books that ſhould be written: and this Diſciple which teſtifieth of theſe things,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8.9, i0. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>chap. Acts</hi> 9. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> and wrote theſe things, we know that his teſtimony is true. And ſo likewiſe the <hi>Acts,</hi> they are a declaration of Chriſts giving power after his Aſcenſion to the Apoſtles, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to bear witneſs of him in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and in all <hi>Iudea, Samaria,</hi> and unto the uttermoſt parts of the earth; and of their preaching and turning many to the righteouſneſs of the faith in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117937:3"/> Chriſt Jeſus: And the <hi>Acts</hi> likewiſe declares of <hi>Pauls</hi> converſion, and his going out to preach the Goſpel among the Gentiles, and to turn them from darkneſs to light,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 12. <hi>chap. Acts</hi> 17. <hi>chap.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. <hi>ver.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and from the power of Satan unto God, who is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all:</hi> And ſo likewiſe they declare of his, and the Apoſtles travells, and their ſufferings, by the <hi>Romanes</hi> and unbeleeving <hi>Iews,</hi> and the baſer ſort of people: and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> and the other Apoſtles writ ſeverall Epiſtles to the Churches, as they ſaw them in their ſeverall conditions, and ſome to particular perſons, as to <hi>Timothy, Titus,</hi> and <hi>Philemon,</hi> and to the twelve <hi>Tribes</hi> ſcattered abroad.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle ſpeaks of the Scripture, and ſaid,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.5. &amp; 8.5 <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.4. &amp; 34.27. &amp; 40.33. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.1, 2. &amp; 36.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>That no propheſie of the Scripture is of any private interpretation, but the holy men of God ſpake them forth as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt;</hi> ſo that <hi>the prophecies written came not of old, by mans own will, nor by the will of man, but by the Holy Ghoſt in the holy men of God, who were moved by the ſame to ſpeak them forth;</hi> ſo that all ſpeaking and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and all interpretations of the things of God, that comes not from the movings and power of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> comes from mans own will, and not from the will and power of God: <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was faithfull in the houſe of God, did all things according to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern ſhewed him, and writ not in his own wil, but in the wil of God. And ſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi> wrote at the Commands of the Lord: And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> wrote not, but at the Command of the Lord, who ſaid unto him, <hi>VVrite all the words in a Roll of a Book that</hi> I <hi>have ſpoken unto thee (againſt</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and againſt</hi> Juda, <hi>and againſt all the nations) from the dayes of</hi> Joſia, <hi>even unto this day.</hi> And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> called <hi>Baruch,</hi> and <hi>Baruch</hi> wrote all the words which the Lord had ſpoken unto <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> from the mouth of <hi>Jeremiah, Baruch</hi> wrote them. Here it is plainly ſeen, that the Scriptures at the firſt was not given forth by mans will, or by private interpretation, but they were given forth by in the will of God, by the holy men of God, as they were moved to ſpeak them forth by the Spirit of God; but ſince the firſt giving of them forth, they have been tranſlated by private interpretors, into the many Languages, and the many Languages have ſeverall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of their private interpretations, with ſome words added to, and ſome words left out: But the ſame Spirit of God that gave them forth, knows its own that it gave forth by the holy men of God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1 <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11.</note> and diſowns the other words that are not of, and from it ſelf, <hi>for no man knoweth the things of God, ſave the Spirit of God;</hi> ſo that it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears, that the Scriptures was never called the Word of God, neither by Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, but they were called by them, <hi>Moſes VVritings, Moſes Law, The Book of the Prophets, The Prophets,</hi> and, <hi>The Pſalms; A Declaration, Teſtimony,</hi> and <hi>Epiſtles:</hi> But the blinde Guides, the prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> that preach for tithes, hire,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117937:4"/> gifts and rewards, they do teach the people, and ſay, <hi>Hearken to the VVord of the Lord; as it is written in a Chapter and a Verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>VVord of the Lord</hi> was before all time; but the Bible, which men call the Scriptures, was not before all time; for <hi>Moſes,</hi> after the Creation many generations, did begin to write the firſt part of it, who was the firſt Writer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 2.3, 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.14. <hi>John</hi> 4.24. <hi>John</hi> 10.28. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> which was in time, and the reſt were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in order of time, as the holy men of God were moved by the Spirit of God to write, and give them forth to be written; therefore the Bible, which is called the Scriptures, is not the <hi>VVord of God,</hi> but is that which teſtifies of the <hi>VVord of God,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus: God is a ſpirit, is the Bible, which is called the Scripture, God? a ſpirit? Nay, for the Word is God: The letter kills, is that Chriſt? the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that giveth life? Nay, then the Letter is not the <hi>VVord of God,</hi> for Chriſt is the Word, and this Word was made fleſh, and dwelt amongſt us, and he is the Light and Life of men, and by him the world was made.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Before the Bible, which is called the Scripture, was writ, the Word was;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1. i. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. i3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. <hi>John</hi> 8 56.58. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1, 2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.27. <hi>John</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.6.9, 10. <hi>Dute.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.160, 162. <hi>verſes. Iſa.</hi> 42. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.45. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4, 5, <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for in the beginning was the VVord, and the VVord was with God,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever;</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the firſt and the laſt:</hi> It is he that calleth the generations from the beginning, who ſaid, <hi>I the Lord am the firſt, and with the laſt</hi> I <hi>am the ſame,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>His Name is called the VVord of God: And they ſhall call his Name Emanuel, (which is, by interpretation) God with us; who took upon him the Seed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>and was before</hi> Abraham <hi>was; Abraham,</hi> ſaid Chriſt, <hi>rejoyced to ſee my day; he ſaw it, and was glad:</hi> The Word of the Lord came to <hi>Abraham</hi> in a Viſion, ſaying, <hi>Fear not,</hi> Abraham, <hi>I am thy Sheild, and thy exceeding great Reward: The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the Righteous run unto it, and are ſafe:</hi> And the Lord appeared again in <hi>Shiloh, for the Lord revealed himſelf to</hi> Samuel <hi>in</hi> Shiloh <hi>by his VVord:</hi> Chriſt ſaid, <hi>No man knows the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal him:</hi> and ſaid Chriſt, <hi>I am the VVay, the Truth and the life; No man cometh to the Father but by me; he that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father;</hi> I <hi>and my Father am one;</hi> I <hi>am in the Father, and the Father in me:</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Lord thy God will raiſe up a Prophet in the midst of thee, of thy brethren, like unto me, unto him ſhall you hearken:</hi> And <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from</hi> Judah, <hi>nor a Law-giver from between his feet, until</hi> Shiloh <hi>come, and unto him ſhall the gathering of the people be:</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thy</hi> Word, <hi>O Lord, is true from the beginning;</hi> I <hi>rejoyce,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>at thy VVord, as one that findeth great ſpoile:</hi> and the ſame Word of the Lord did all the prophets ſee, and hear, and bear witneſs to, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Scriptures were written to bear Teſtimony of this Word to after Generations that ſhould come, and likewiſe of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117937:4"/> righteous judgments of God which came upon them that oppoſed the ſame; which Examples were written for our learning, upon whom the ends of the world is come, unto whom the Scripture is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by inſpiration of the Spirit, that the Man of God may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thorowly, furniſhed unto every good work, which is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproofe, for correction, and for inſtruction in Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As Chriſt is the <hi>VVord of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 8. i2. <hi>John</hi> 1.5.9.12. <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. i3. <hi>John</hi> 16.9, 10, 11.12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> i.19.</note> ſo he is the <hi>Light of the VVorld,</hi> yea, the true <hi>Light, that inlightneth every one that cometh into the world: VVhoſoever followeth him ſhall not walk in Darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of life; and to as many as receive him, and beleeve on his Name, to them he gives power to become the Sons of God;</hi> but theſe whoſe Underſtanding is darkned, even ſuch <hi>as ſit in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of death; the Light ſhineth in the darkneſs, but the darkneſs comprehendeth it not;</hi> but al things that are reproved, are made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the Light; the Light makes ſin manifeſt in the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and convinceth of ſin, and condemns ſin in the conſcience: but thoſe that walk in darkneſs hate the Light, and will not bring their deeds to it, becauſe they are evill, and the Light reproves them, and to ſuch the Light is their condemnation.</p>
            <p>Therefore take heed to this Light, which ſhineth in a dark place, untill the day dawn, and the Day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts; while you have the Light, beleeve in the Light,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 12.36. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.7.</note> that ye may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the children of the Light, and the children of the Day, who bear witneſs to the Light. <hi>Iohn,</hi> a man ſent of God to bear witneſs of the Light, who ſaid, <hi>that was the true Light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world:</hi> And <hi>David,</hi> he bare witneſs, and ſaid, <hi>The Lord is my light and my lamp, he will inlighten my darkneſs, he is my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and the ſtrength of my life:</hi> and again ſaid he,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. i. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.39. <hi>John</hi> 1.1.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60.19, 20. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.31, 32. <hi>John</hi> 1.10, 11, <hi>&amp;</hi> 17 <hi>verſes.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thy VVord is a Lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my pathes.</hi> And John ſaid, <hi>God is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all.</hi> And Iſaiah ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſhall be unto thee an everlaſting Light, and thy God thy glory. Chriſt is given for a Light to the Gentiles, and for ſalvation to the ends of the earth;</hi> to which <hi>Simeon</hi> bore witneſs, and ſaid, <hi>Mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which thou haſt prepared before the face of all people; a light to light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people</hi> Iſrael: which Light was in the beginning, <hi>and is come to his own, and his own received him not:</hi> he is in the world, and the world was made by him, and the world knows him not, by whom Grace and Truth is come, CHRIT JESUS.</p>
            <p>Thirdly: Seeing that Chriſt is the <hi>Light of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>John</hi> 5.25.</note> and the <hi>VVord of God,</hi> which is to be hearkned unto and obeyed: therefore unto him hearken and hear, that your ſouls may live, <hi>For they that hear the voice of the Son of God, they ſhall live: the word is nigh thee,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117937:5"/> in thy heart and in thy mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dute.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>John</hi> 17.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8. <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.26, 27. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>John</hi> 15.18.25. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.42. <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.9. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.2, 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31. <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.23, 24 26. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.2i, 22, 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21, 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>that thou mayeſt do it:</hi> therefore keep thy minde in from wandering abroad, <hi>for the wiſe mans eye is in his head; Chriſt is the head of every man, hearken and attend to his word, keep thy heart with all dilligence, for out of it are the iſſues of life; he that hath the Son hath life, Chriſt in you the hope of glory; he is one in all;</hi> except ye be Reprobates you may know this: <hi>For we being many, are all one in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, the righteouſneſs which is of faith, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth on this wiſe, <hi>Say not in thy heart who ſhall aſcend into heaven, that is to bring Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt down from a love; or who ſhall deſcend into the deep, that is to bring up Chriſt again from the dead:</hi> but ſaith it, <hi>The word is nigh thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that is the word of Faith which we preach; without controverſie, great is the myſtery of godlineſs, which hath been hid from ages aad generations, but is now made manifeſt unto his Saints, which is, God manifeſt in the fleſh, juſtified in the ſpirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, rejected by the world, but received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to glory.</hi> And <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>His word was in my heart, as a burning fire ſhut up in my bones, and</hi> I <hi>was weary with forbearing, and</hi> I <hi>could not ſtay.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord ſpeak by me, and his word was in my tongue; the Rock of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſpeak to me;</hi> and that Rock is Chriſt; <hi>he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith,</hi> (God is a ſpirit) who ſaith, <hi>this is my beloved Son, hear ye him in all things, Ceaſe from man, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils, and hearken to the VVord of the Lord, which is nigh thee, in thy heart and in thy mouth:</hi> Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Come learn of me, heare, that your ſouls may live: to day if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, but be ſwift to hear, and ſlow to ſpeak: ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord, for they that wait upon the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength:</hi> and do not hearken any longer to the blinde guides, the prieſts, which cries, Lo here, hearken to the Word of the Lord ſaith one, as it is written in the chapter and the verſe: Lo here, ſaith another, hearken to the Word of the Lord, as it is written in this chapter and this verſe: See here ſaith one, it is written, this chapter and this verſe: See there, ſaith another, as it is written in this chapter and this verſe. But they are falſe prophets, riſe up to ſeduce, if it were poſſible, the very Elect: but ſaith Chriſt, go not forth, beleeve them not, the kingdom of heaven is within you, the Law is written in the heart, according to the Covenant of God, <hi>Moſes, David, Jeremiah,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſaid, the Word of the Lord is in the heart and in the mouth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 11 <hi>verſe. Numb.</hi> 22.38. &amp; 24.17, 18, 19. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11.</note> and yet the prieſts of the Nations are not aſhamed to ſay, It is written in a chapter and a verſe: and although the prieſts of this Nation run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for honour and rewards, yet they are more blinde than <hi>Balaam,</hi> and have not got by all their ſtudy and learning, ſo much of the knowledge of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117937:5"/> Word, as he, who ſaid to <hi>Balaak</hi> (after the Lord had turned him from going to curſe Iſrael) <hi>the word that God putteth into my mouth, that ſhall</hi> I <hi>speak:</hi> O ye prieſts that preach for hire, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine for money, and are by men called, and ſay your ſelves, you are miniſters and preachers of the Word of God. Are you not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to ſee that <hi>Balaam</hi> had more knowledge of the Word then you have be aſhamed, and bluſh, and ſtop your mouths, and be ſilent before the Lord God, and utter no more of your own words before him, and repent of your lying and blaſphemy, for Chriſt, who is the Word of God, is but one, and is not divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into chapters and verſes, which are many, therefore do not deceive the people any longer, by the divination of your own brains, for the Lord God will make the diviners mad, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſdome of the wiſe, and bring to nought the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the prudent.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Scriptures, which is viſible, is a viſible writing; but the Word of the Lord is inviſibly written in the heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.29.</note> and is like a Fire, yea, Our God is a conſuming Fire; and who amongſt us ſhall dwell with the devouring Fire? Who amongſt us ſhall dwell with everlaſting Burnings? Who may abide the day of his coming? For behold, the day cometh, that ſhall burn as an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly ſhall be as the ſtuble, and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3 &amp; 4. <hi>chap. Nahum.</hi> 1.5.6.</note> ſo that it ſhal leave them neither root nor branch: <hi>The mountains quake at him, the hills melt, the earth is burnt at his preſence, yea, the world, &amp; all that dwell therein; who can stand before his indignation, and who can abide the fierceneſs of his anger? his fury is poured out like fire, ſaith the Lord of Hosts; who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth, for he is like a Refiners fire, and like Fullers Sope; and he ſhall ſit as a Refiner, and a Purifier of ſilver, and he ſhall purifie the Sons of</hi> Levi, <hi>and purge them as gold and ſilver, that they may offer unto the Lord an Offering in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> [but do not think that I take the prieſts of England to be the Sons of Levi] <hi>for the Lord God, who is coming to judgement, will be a ſwift witneſs against the ſorcerers, and against the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and againſt the falſe ſwearers, and against thoſe that defraud the ſervant of his wages, and oppreſs the widow and the fatherleſs, and thoſe that turn aſide the stranger from his right, and fear not me, ſaith the Lord of hosts.</hi> Chriſt is come to ſet fire on the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.49. <hi>Mic.</hi> 1.3, 4. <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> and its al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready kindled, and the Mountains ſhall be moulton under him, and the Valleys ſhall be cleft as wax before the fire, and as the waters that are poured down a ſteep place; and what will become of you enemies of God, that walk in darkneſs and hate the Light, and will not hearken to, and obey the Word of the Lord: Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is revealed from heaven with his mighty An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9 <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117937:6"/> in flames of fire, to render vengeance upon them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judge the ſecrets of all mens hearts by Chriſt Jeſus, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Goſpel; for we are ſure that the judgments of God are according to Truth, Chriſt is Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.4.</note>Wo unto the bloudy City, that is full of Lies and Robbery, from which the prey departeth not. Wo unto you Drunkards of England, awake, weep and howle, for the Drunkard ſhall come to poverty, and never inherit the Kingdom of God. Wo unto you Whoremongers and Adulterers, for the Lord God will you judge.</p>
            <p>Wo unto you that ſwear and ſteal, for the Curſe of God is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the houſe of the thief,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.3, 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14. <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.51. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.23, 24. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.18.</note> and into the houſe of the ſwearer, and every one that ſweareth ſhall be cut off, and every one that Stealeth ſhall be cut off, and never in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom of God. Wo unto you hypocrites, for fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath ſurpriſed you, and hell is your portion, where is weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing. Wo unto you rich men, weep and howle, for the miſery that is coming upon you; It is hard for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of heaven. Wo unto you proud and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ones, God reſiſteth the proud, and beholdeth them afar off: Pride goeth before deſtruction, and a haughty ſpirit before a fall; you wicked ones ſhall be as ſtuble before the fire. Wo unto you murderers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Habb.</hi> 1.13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12.</note> that have murdered the innocent and ſlain the juſt, becauſe their works are good and acceptable with God, and yours evill, the voice of the blood of the righteous cryeth, and the cry thereof is heard from under the earth unto the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and all the blood that hath been ſhed from the day of righteous <hi>Abel</hi> unto this day, ſhalbe required of this generation.</p>
            <p>O ye Prieſts of England, who are called Miniſters, but are the Idol-ſhepherds thereof, for as Iſrael brake off their Ear-rings from their wives, their Sons, and their daughters, and made them a Calfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Read the</hi> 17 &amp; 18. <hi>chapter of</hi> Judges.</note> and worſhipped it, ſo have the people of England with their Gold, Silver, Tithes, Gifts and Rewards, made you, who they call Miniſters, their Idols, and have ſet you up in the higheſt ſeats in their high places, which they call their Church, which is like <hi>Micah,</hi> the man of <hi>Mount Ephraims</hi> houſe of gods, which was made by the Founders and the Gravers: ſo in the Steeplehouſes in England are ſet up (by the Gravers, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and the Painters) Pictures and Images of men, women and children, and ſeverall ſorts of other creatures; and upon them the people look ſometimes, and up to the Prieſts other times, and to the prieſts they hearken, and not to God, for he is not in all their thoughts; and they ſay of the prieſts, theſe are our Teachers, theſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117937:6"/> are our leaders which will lead us to heaven; juſt as the children of Iſrael ſaid of their golden Calf, Theſe are thy Gods, O Iſrael, which brought thee up out of the Land of Aegypt: So <hi>Micah,</hi> the Idolater, when he had got a <hi>Levite</hi> to be his prieſt, which he hired for ten ſhekles of ſilver by the yeer, and a ſute of Apparel, and his Victuals, for which the Levite became his prieſt; then ſaid <hi>Micah,</hi> Now know I that the Lord will do me good. So the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of England think, while they have prieſts that preaches for hire, they think it will go wel with them; but the time came that <hi>Micah's</hi> Gods and his prieſts was carried away from him. Ah ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh people! why have you forſaken Chriſt, the true ſhepherd and Biſhop of your ſouls, who is the way to the Father, and no man cometh to the Father but by him? wherefore do you ſpend your money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfies not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.2.</note> to follow thoſe blinde guides who lead the blinde, and both will fall into the ditch, for of them you are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth. Wo unto the Idol-ſhepherds that leaveth the Flock, the ſword ſhall be upon his Arm, and upon his right Eye; his Arm ſhall be clean dried up,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.17</note> and his right Eye ſhall be utterly dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: Read your portion you Idol-ſhepherds of England, who ſay the Scripture is the Word of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which teſtifieth contrary to your ſaying, that Chriſt Jeſus is the Word, and the Word is God, which is as a fire.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The Word of the Lord is like a Hammer, that break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Rocks in pieces, and the Rocks are thrown down by it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29 <hi>Nah.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Hearken all you who have made your faces harder then a Rock, and refuſe to return to the Lord that made you, and have made your hearts as an Adamant-ſtone, leſt ye ſhould hear the Law from the pure Law-giver, Chriſt Jeſus, by him ſhall ye be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces, as with a Rod of Iron, and daſhed in pieces like a potters veſſel: The Lord, the true God, the living God, and an everlaſting King, at his wrath the earth ſhall tremble, and the Nations ſhall not abide his indignation; he hath made the earth by his power, he eſtabliſhed the world by his wiſdome, and ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out the heaven by his underſtanding; he ſaith of the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Iacob,</hi> thou art my battel Ax, and the weapons of war:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5. &amp; 119.57. <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.43, 44 45. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.15 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</note> And <hi>David</hi> ſaid, The Lord is my portion, and the lot of mine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and again he ſaid, Thou art my portion, O Lord. Chriſt is Lord, and <hi>David</hi> called him ſo; The Lord ſaid unto my Lord; and this Lord is <hi>Iacobs</hi> portion, whom the Lord ſaid, By thee will I break in pieces the Nations, and with thee will I deſtroy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; and with thee wil I break in pieces the Horſe and his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117937:7"/> and with thee will I break in pieces the chariot and his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; with thee alſo will I break in pieces man and woman; and with thee wil I break in pieces young man and old; and with thee wil I break in pieces the young man and the maid. Hearken you prieſts of England, who are called Miniſters, and ſay the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the Word of God, but the Word of the Lord is inviſible, and cannot be ſeen with your carnall eyes, and by it wil the Lord break in pieces the Shepherd and his Flock,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> and he will gather his Flock from your mouthes, and it ſhall become no longer a prey unto you, and he will feed his ſheep upon the mountains of Iſrael, and lead them to the ſtil waters; and he will likewiſe break in pieces the husbandman, and his yoke of Oxen; and with thee will I break in pieces, ſaith the Lord, the Captains and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 10 34. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.51, 52, 53.</note> and ſaid Chriſt, Think not that I am come to ſend peace on the earth, I am not come to ſend peace, but a ſword, to make diviſion, for from henceforth there ſhall be five in one houſe, divided, three againſt two, and two againſt three; the Father ſhall be divided againſt the Son, and the Son againſt the Father; the Daughter againſt the Mother, and the Mother againſt the Daughter: the Mother-in-Law againſt the Daughter-in-Law, and where the Word of the Lord comes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> it ſeperates and divides aſunder. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, that the Word of God is quick and powerfull, and ſharper then any two-edged-ſword, piercing, even to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joints and marrow; and it is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart, and this <hi>David</hi> witneſſed, and ſaid, O Lord, thou haſt ſearched me, and known me, thou underſtandeſt my thoughts afar off, and art acquainted with all my wayes.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The VVord of the Lord is very pure, ſaid <hi>David,</hi> therefore thy ſervant loveth it:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.140. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. <hi>John</hi> 15.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17, 17. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25, 26, 27. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.</note> Chriſt Jeſus is the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever: And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid, The VVord of our God ſhall ſtand for ever. And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Being born again, not of corruptible ſeed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God, which liveth and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for ever: the word of the Lord, which is pure, makes clean:</hi> ſaid Chriſt, <hi>Ye are clean through the word.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>the very God of peace ſanctifice you wholly:</hi> Chriſt Jeſus is the mighty God, the prince of peace, who ſaid, Father, ſanctifie them through thy VVord, thy VVord is Truth: Chriſt is Truth, the blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth from all ſin: <hi>He loved the Church, and gave himſelf for it, that he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the VVord, that he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, not having spot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy, and without blemiſh; holy as he is holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in all manner of converſation;</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117937:7"/> and ſo the Saints of Chriſt are, by the ſprinckling of the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, made clean from al filthineſs, and from all Idols, ſaith the Lord, wil I cleanſe you; by the which Will we are ſanctified,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> through the offering of the body of Jeſus Chriſt once for all; <hi>For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified, for he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified, are all one, for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call them brethren, which brethren do beleeve that they need not go into Purgatory to be cleanſed from their ſins after death, for they know that they are already tranſlated from death to life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>and have the witneſs in themſelves, that although they were filthy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>yet now they know that they are waſhed, ſanctified, and juſtified in the Name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and by the spirit of our God; and being made free from ſin,</hi> by the Law of the ſpirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>are become the ſervants of Righteouſneſs: Seeing,</hi> ſaid Peter, <hi>ye have purified your ſouls in obeying the Truth through the Spirit, unto unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed love of the Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Mat</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſee that ye love one another fervently with a pure heart; the pure in heart they are bleſſed, and ſhall ſee God, but no unclean thing ſhall inherit the kingdom of God;</hi> for without are Dogs, and Sorcerers, and Whoremongers, and Murderers, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a lie; and out of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome you are,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, i0. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15.</note> and ſuch are you who ſay you ſhall never be free from ſin in this life; <hi>For as the tree falls, ſo it ſhall lye, whether it fall to the North, or to the South:</hi> Therefore cleanſe your hands you ſinners, and purifie your hearts, you double minded, and come to Chriſt, that you may be made clean through the Word, and have life.</p>
            <p>Seventhly: The Scripture, which is viſible,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>Coll.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6.</note> made not the world, but by the Word of God the Heavens, and the Earth, and all things therein were made; For ſaid <hi>Iohn, In the beginning was the VVord, and the VVord was with God; all things were made by him, and nothing was made without him that was made; for it was the Spirit of God that moved upon the face of the waters;</hi> and Jeremiah ſaid, That <hi>God hath made the earth by his power, he eſtabliſhed the world by his wiſdome;</hi> Chriſt is the Power of God, and the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God: And <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>By the VVord of the Lord were the heavens made, and all the hoſts of them by the breath of his Mouth:</hi> And Paul ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3.</note> 
               <hi>Through faith we underſtand that the worlds were framed by the VVord of God, ſo that the things which are ſeen, were not made of the things which do appear; For by him were all things created that are in heaven, and that are in earth, viſible and inviſible, whether they be thrones, or dominions; or principallities, or powers, all things were created by him, and for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117937:8"/>
            <p>Eightly: And as all things were made by the Word of God, which Word was before any Letter of the Scripture was written; ſo by the ſame Word of his Power are all things upheld; <hi>For in him we live and move and have our being,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24, 26, 28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7.</note> ſaid <hi>Peter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For of this thing they are willingly ignorant of that by the VVord of God the heavens were of old, and the earth ſtanding out of the water, and in the water; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eby the world that then was, being overflowed with water, periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but the heavens and the earth which are now, by the ſame VVord are kept in ſtore, reſerved unto fire againſt the day of judgement, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ungodly men;</hi> under which ungodly men, the Prophets and Apoſtles, and Servants of the Lord, ever in all generations, ſuffered cruel mockings, bonds, and impriſonments, and death for obeying the Commands of the Lord, and bearing their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Chriſt Jeſus the Son of God, and the Word of God, and likewiſe for crying out againſt the ſins and abominations which was committed in thoſe dayes, both by Kings, Rule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Judges, Prieſts, Prophets and people and as the ſins and abominations was then, ſo it is now in theſe dayes acted by the like generation of Heathens that rage,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10.</note> and people that imagine vain things; the Kings and the Rulers fit and take counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed, and in ſo doing they think they do God good ſervice, and for their ſo doing are accounted good Chriſtians by their own generation, both of Prieſts and people; but they are no chriſtians that do ſuch things, for if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature, and the old man with his deeds is put off, and the New man put on, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and of him they learn who is meek and lowly, and to be holy in all manner of converſation, and to love the brethren, and to entertain ſtrangers, and thoſe Rulers that ſo learn, are a terrour to the evil doers, and a protection to them that do wel, for he that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God, for thoſe that were ordained of God, and ruled in the fear of God, did not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon the Servants of God, and his prophets, but received them, and protected them: But thoſe Rulers and people, who without the fear of God were, and ruled in their own wills, they whipt and ſtockt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.10, 11.</note> and put in priſons and dungeons, and chains, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, deſpiſed, and mocked the meſſengers of the Lord, untill the wrath of God aroſe againſt them, and there was no remedy; as you may ſee hereafter appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> he put none of the Servants of the Lord in <hi>Priſon;</hi> for as he ſaid in his Tent doore in the heate of the daye, in the plains of <hi>Mamro,</hi> where the Lord appeared unto him, and he lift up his eyes, and looked, and do t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e men ſtood by him; and when he ſaw them he ran from the Tent-doore and met them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117937:8"/> and ſaid, <hi>My Lord, if I have found favour in thy ſight, paſs not, I pray thee from thy ſervant;</hi> and Abraham ſaid, <hi>Let a little water I pray you be fetched, and waſh your feet, and reſt your ſelves under the Tree, and I will fetch a morſel of bread, and comfort your hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read Gen. <hi>18.</hi> chap.</note> 
               <hi>and after that you ſhall paſs on, for therefore are you come to your Servant; and</hi> Abraham <hi>haſtened into the Tent, and ſaid, Make ready quickly three meaſures of fine meale, kneed it, and make Cakes upon the hearth; and</hi> Abraham <hi>ran unto the herd, and fetch a Calfe, tender and good; and gave it to a young man, and be haſted to dreſs it; and</hi> Abraham <hi>took butter and milk, and the Calfe which was dreſſed, and ſet it before them, and he ſtood by them under the Tree, and they did eat, and the men roſe up from thence, and looked towards</hi> Sodome, <hi>and</hi> Abraham <hi>went with them to bring them in their way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And juſt <hi>Lot</hi> he put none in priſon:<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>19.</hi> chap.</note> 
               <hi>For there came to Sodome at even two Angels, and</hi> Lot <hi>ſate in the Gate of Sodome, and</hi> Lot <hi>ſeeing them roſe up and met them; and he ſaid, Behold, now my Lords turn in I pray you into your Servants houſe, and tarry all night and waſh your feet, &amp; ye ſhal riſe up early, &amp; go on your wayes; &amp; he preſſed upon them greatly, and they turned in unto him, and entered into his houſe, and he made them a feaſt, and did break unleavened bread, and they did eat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> put none of the Servants nor prophets of the Lord in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> ii.24. <hi>to the</hi> 30.</note> for when the young man ran and told him that <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> do propheſie in the camp, and would have had <hi>Moſes</hi> to forbid them, and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>Envieſt thou for my ſake? would to God that all the Lords people were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his ſpirit upon them; and Moſes and the Elders of Iſrael went into the Camp,</hi> but did not forbid them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> he put none of the Lords prophets in priſon;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>Nathan</hi> the prophet came, and declared unto him the parable of the Ewe-lamb, he ſtraightway confeſſed his ſin, and owned his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon himſelf, by his own words, out of his own mouth; neither do I finde that <hi>Solomon</hi> put any in priſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſhua</hi> he put none of the Lords ſervants in priſon; nor <hi>Gideon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 5.13, i4, i5. <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.8. i1, 12, 13.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> he neither put the Angel, nor the prophet of the Lord in priſon, but he threw down the Altar of <hi>Baal,</hi> and cut down the Grove that was by it.</p>
            <p>Neither did <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> nor <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.</note> nor <hi>Ioſiah</hi> put any of the prophets of the Lord in priſon, neither did any of theſe Kings and Rulers afore mentioned, make any law, ſtatute, or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or ſend forth any <hi>Proclamation</hi> to their Judges, Juſtices, Sheriffs, or other Officers, to take the Prophets and Servants of the Lord, as they wandered up and down in ſheep-skins and goat-skins from place to place, in the work and ſervice of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117937:9"/> Lord, and to put them in priſon, or to whip them, and to ſend them away with Paſſes like Vagabonds; And <hi>Abraham, Lot, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Ioſhua, Gideon, David, Solomon, Hezekiah, Iehoſaphat,</hi> and <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> were all Rulers that feared God, and were not of them that miſuſed the Prophets, nor deſpiſed the Word, nor mocked the Meſſengers of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But thoſe that do in theſe dayes impriſon, mock, and miſuſe the Prophets and Miniſters of God, (and deſpiſe his word which they declare and obey) are no Chriſtians; neither were they Chriſtians that did ſo in former Generations; for the firſt King or Ruler that I read of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 39 &amp; 40. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> who had got an invented Priſon, was <hi>Pharoah</hi> King of Aegypt, and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> being falſly accuſed by his filthy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Miſtris, was put into the Aegyptian Kings Priſon, among the Kings Priſoners by his Maſter <hi>Pottiphar,</hi> the Captain of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roahs</hi> Guard, and <hi>Pharoah</hi> being offended with his Butler and Baker, in his wrath put them in Priſon; and he that was offended and did this in his rage, was no Chriſtian, but a dark Aegyptian King without the fear of God.</p>
            <p>And the uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtines</hi> had not the fear of God, that plowed with <hi>Sampſons</hi> Heifer, and caught <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and put him in priſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 26.21.</note> and bound him with Fetters of Braſs, theſe <hi>Philiſtines</hi> that did this, were no Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ahab,</hi> as King <hi>Pharoah</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> had got Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.27. <hi>Coll.</hi> 3.5.</note> ſo had he got a Priſon, and ſaid of <hi>Micaiah</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, <hi>Take this fellow into the Priſon, and feed him with bread of affliction, and with water of affliction, untill I come in peace:</hi> And <hi>Ahab</hi> was an Idolater, and no Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Aſa</hi> fel off from the Lord, and relyed on the King of <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. <hi>chap Pſal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</hi> 31.1.</note> for the which he was reproved by <hi>Hanani</hi> the Seer; then was <hi>Aſa</hi> wrath with the Seer, and put him in the priſon-houſe, for he was in a rage with him becauſe of this thing: and <hi>Aſa</hi> oppreſſed ſome of the people the ſame time. Was <hi>Aſa,</hi> that oppreſſed the people, and that fel off from the Lord, and went down to Aegypt and Aſſyria for help, a Chriſtian, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>And <hi>Zedekiah</hi> did that which was evill in the ſight of the Lord God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.12. <hi>&amp;c. Ier.</hi> 37. &amp; 38. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> and when <hi>Ieremiah</hi> came to him, and ſpeak to him from the mouth of the Lord, he humbled not himſelf, but conſulted with his Princes, and at their requeſt <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was by them put in a Dungeon, where they let him down with cords, and he ſtuck faſt in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, and <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and his Princes that did this to the Lords Prophet, and deſpiſed his word, and tranſgreſſed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much after all the Abominations of the Heathen, were no Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117937:9"/>
            <p>And <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Tetrarch,</hi> that Fox and Murderer, he put <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> in priſon; and <hi>Herod</hi> the King ſtretched forth his hand to vex certain of the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> i4.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 12.1, 2, 3, 4, 21, 22, 23.</note> and he killed <hi>Iames</hi> the Brother of <hi>John,</hi> and when he ſaw it pleaſed the Jews, he caught <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle of Chriſt, likewiſe, and put him in priſon; and theſe two <hi>Herods</hi> was neither of them Chriſtians that did this, I am ſure.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Romanes,</hi> when they ſaw that <hi>Paul</hi> had in the Name of Jeſus commanded the Spirit of <hi>Divination</hi> to go out of the Damſel, which did likewiſe the ſame hour,<note place="margin">Read Acts. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>6</hi> chap.</note> and that thereby the hope of their gains was gone, then they caught <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and drew them into the Market-place to the Magiſtrates, and brought them to the Governours, ſaying, Theſe men, being Jews do exceedingly trouble our City, and teach Ordinances which are not lawfull for us to receive, neither to obſerve, being <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> and all the people roſe up againſt them, and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours rent off their clothes, and commanded that they ſhould be beaten with Rods, and when they had beaten them ſore, they caſt them in Priſon, and commanded the Jaylor to keep them ſafely, who having received ſuch a commandment, caſt them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inner-priſon, and made their feet faſt in the Stocks. Theſe <hi>Romans, Magiſtrates, Governours,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> were no Chriſtians, that uſed the Apoſtles and Servants of Chriſt ſo.</p>
            <p>And all theſe <hi>Heathen Rulers, Kings, Magiſtrates,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> who without the fear of God were, and bore their Swords in vain, were no Chriſtians, were not contented with putting the <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles, Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> of the Moſt High God in Priſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. i, 2.8.13 14, 15.</note> but they invented in their rage and cruelty further puniſhments, and death unto them: For <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he was not only put in Priſon, but he was bound in Priſon, and he was brought before <hi>Pharoah</hi> haſtily out of the <hi>Dungeon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read Dan. the <hi>6.</hi> chap.</note> And they were <hi>Philiſtines</hi> that put <hi>Sampſons</hi> eyes out, and bound him with Fetters of Braſs; and they were Idolaters, and ſuch as tranſgreſſed very much, after all the abominations of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and mocked the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of God, and miſuſed his <hi>Prophets,</hi> and deſpiſed his Word, that fed <hi>Mica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> with bread and water of affliction, and let <hi>Jeremiah</hi> with cords down into the <hi>Dungeon</hi> to ſtick faſt in the mire. And they were <hi>Babylonians</hi> and <hi>Caldeans,</hi> that invented the <hi>Fiery Fornace,</hi> and put <hi>Hananiah, Miſhael,</hi> and <hi>Azariah</hi> into it, for refuſing to fall down and worſhip the <hi>Golden Image</hi> that <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> had ſet up; <hi>Then</hi> Nebuchadnezar, <hi>the Princes, the Governours, and the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, the Judges, the Councellors, the Treaſurers, the Sheriffs, and all the Rulers of the Provinces, were all at making the Proclamation, and the Caldeans they accuſed the three Jews,</hi> Shadrack, Meſhek, <hi>and</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bednigo,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117937:10"/> 
               <hi>and the King in his rage and fury commanded them to be brought before him, and he was full of fiery, the form of his Viſage was changed, and he commanded the moſt mighty men of his Army to binde them, and caſt them into the fiery burning Fornace:</hi> and by the ſame generation of men was <hi>Daniel</hi> caſt into the Lyons Den, for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and giving thanks unto God: And theſe <hi>Babylonians</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> were no <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they were <hi>Libertines, Syrenians,</hi> and <hi>Alexandreans,</hi> and men of <hi>Cylitia,</hi> and of <hi>Aſia,</hi> that ſuborned men, and ſtirred up the people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 6, 7. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> the Elders, and the Scribes, and caught <hi>Stephen,</hi> and brought him before the Councel, and when they heard the things which he ſpeak, they gnaſhed on him with their teeth, and ran upon him with one accord, and caſt him out of the City, and ſtoned him to death: And they were Jews, and Gentiles together, which ſtoned <hi>Paul,</hi> and drew him out of the city, ſuppoſing he had been dead.<note place="margin">Acts <hi>14.</hi> chap.</note> And they were <hi>Herods</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> that cut off <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> head, and killed <hi>James</hi> the brother of <hi>John</hi> with the Sword, and put <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> in the Stocks, and whipt them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were put in, and ſuch, with the Jews, chief Prieſts, and Scribes, crucified Chriſt the Son of God. And they were the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Papiſts that ſet up ſtakes in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and tyed the Martyrs to them, and ſet Faggots and ſire to them, and burnt them.</p>
            <p>And as the Servants of the Lord (in whom was the righteous Seed) ſuffered death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Iude</hi> 18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.29, 30, 31. <hi>Luke</hi> 23. ii.</note> bonds, ſtripes, ſtoning and impriſonment, with other tortures, in all ages, by wicked and ungodly men, ſo likewiſe did they who were born after the ſpirit, ſuffer cruel mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſcoffiings, by thole who are born after the fleſh, who walk after their own ungodly luſts, and ſuch are perſecutors, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> the Son of <hi>Hagar</hi> the Aegyptian, whom <hi>Sarah,</hi> the Free-Woman, ſaw mocking <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in whom was the Righteous Seed; and they are Sons of <hi>Hagar</hi> who walk after their own ungodly luſts now, that are ſeen mocking the Servants of the Lord in theſe dayes, them in whom the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Seed is in, begotten by the immortall Word, and born of the Free-Woman, but whoſo mocketh the poor, deſpiſeth his Maker, who bleſſeth the poor in Spirit; you ſcoffers and mockers, you may Read your Portion in the firſt of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> from the twenty ſecond verſe to the latter end.</p>
            <p>All theſe, who thus ſuffered, were no Vagabonds, but were faithfull diligent meſſengers, and painful Labourers in the Lords Vineyard, which was large, and his Harveſt great, in which they wandered about, labouring and reaping down his harveſt, and gathering the Wheat into the Garners, wandering about in ſheep-skins,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117937:10"/> and goat-skins, from city to city, and from one countrey into another. <hi>Elijah</hi> he wandered about where ever the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him, and did the Lords meſſages; ſee how he travelled about, who was an inhabitant at <hi>Gilead,</hi> and at the command of the Lord he went to <hi>Samaria</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi> to tell him there ſhould be neither dew nor rain, and then at the command of the Lord he turned Eaſtward, to hide himſelf by the River <hi>Cherith</hi> over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jordan,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Zarephath,</hi> which is in <hi>Zidon,</hi> where the Widow ſuſtained him for a certain time; and after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes, he in the third yeer went to <hi>Samaria</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> which is in <hi>Judah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18, &amp; 19. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> and from thence he went a dayes journey into the Wilderneſs, and lay undet the Juniper Tree, and from thence he roſe up, and travelled forty dayes and forty nights unto <hi>Horeb,</hi> the mount of God, and there he entred into a Cave, and lodged there, and the Lord went by, and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtrong winde rent the mountains, and break the rocks, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwatd came an Earthquake, and after the Earthquake came fire, &amp; after the fire, came a ſtill ſoft Voice, and <hi>Elijah</hi> heard it, and the Lord ſaid to him, Go, return by the Wilderneſs to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and when thou comeſt there, Anoint <hi>Hazell</hi> King over <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> And <hi>Iehu,</hi> Son of <hi>Nimſhi</hi> ſhalt thou Anoint King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. <hi>chap</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> the Son of <hi>Shaphat</hi> ſhalt thou Anoint to be Prophet in thy room. So he departed thence, and found <hi>Eliſha</hi> Plowing wirh twelve yoke of Oxen before him; and <hi>Elijah</hi> went towards him and caſt his Mantle upon him, and he left the Oxen, and ran af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. And the Lord ſent <hi>Elijah</hi> again to meet <hi>Ahah</hi> King of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, which is in Samaria, for the Lord ſaid, Lo, he is in the Vineyard of <hi>Naboth;</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> went and did his Meſſage to <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.20 21.</note> as the Lord commanded; and after the Lord ſent him to meet the Meſſengers of <hi>Ahazia,</hi> King of Samaria, as they were going to <hi>Baal Zebub</hi> the God of <hi>Ebron,</hi> and to them he delivered his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that the Lord commanded, and he went to the top of a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſate there; and the meſſengers returned to the King and told him all that <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid of him; and the King ſaid, What manner of man was he that met you and told you theſe words? and they ſaid, He was an hairy man, girded about his loins with a leathern girdle; then ſaid the King, It is <hi>Elijah</hi> the Tiſhbite: and the King ſent a Captain and fiftie men to fetch him, but the Captain and his fiftie men were devoured by fire, and the King ſent a Captain and other fiftie men, who were devoured by fire alſo: And he ſent a third Captain and fiftie men, and the third Captain fell on his knees before <hi>Elijah,</hi> and intreated him that the life of him and his fiftie men might be precious in his ſight,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> King. <hi>i</hi> chap. &amp; <hi>2</hi> chap.</note> and then the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Elijah,</hi> Go down with him to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117937:11"/> King, and be not afraid of his preſence; and <hi>Elijah</hi> went down with him and delivered his Meſſage. And <hi>Elijah</hi> went with <hi>Eliſha</hi> from <hi>Gilgal</hi> to <hi>Bethel,</hi> and from <hi>Bethel</hi> to <hi>Jericho,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Iordan,</hi> and they two ſtood there, and <hi>Elijah</hi> took his cloak and wrapt it together, and ſmote the Waters, and they were divided hither and thither, and they two went over on dry dry land; and when they were paſſed over, as they went walking and talking, behold there appeared a Chariot of fire, and Horſes of fire, and did ſeparate them two, and <hi>Elijah</hi> went up with a Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde into Heaven. And <hi>Elijah</hi> that travelled thus up and down, to and fro, was no Vagabond, nor Idle, Diſorderly perſon. And <hi>Eliſha</hi> took up the cloak of <hi>Elijah</hi> that fell from him, and ſmote the Waters of <hi>Iordan,</hi> and went over, and went to <hi>Iericho,</hi> and tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried there; and the men of the city told him the Waters were nought, and he caſt Salt into the Spring of Waters, and ſaid, Thus ſaith the Lord, I have healed theſe Waters, death ſhall no more come thereof, nor barrenneſs to the ground; and he went from thence to <hi>Bethel,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Mount Carmel,</hi> and from thence he returned to <hi>Samaria:</hi> And on a time <hi>Eliſha</hi> came to <hi>Shunem,</hi> and there was a woman of great eſtimation, conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to eat bread, and ſhe ſaid to her husband, behold, now I know that this is an holy man of God, (that paſſeth by us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually) and he went to <hi>Mount Carmel,</hi> and the womans childe being dead, ſhe went to him and told him, and he came into the houſe where the child lay dead, and by him, through faith, the child was raiſed to life: And afterward <hi>Eliſha</hi> returned to <hi>Gigal,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> was in <hi>Samaria,</hi> when <hi>Naaman</hi> came to him to be cured of his leproſie, and he ſent him word, to go waſh ſeven times in <hi>Iordan</hi> and thy fleſh ſhall come again, and thou ſhalt be clean. And after that <hi>Eliſha</hi> went with the children of the Prophets to <hi>Iordan:</hi> And after he went into <hi>Dothan,</hi> where the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> ſent Horſes and Chariots, and a mighty Hoſt, and compaſſed the City, but the Lord ſmote them with blindneſs, and <hi>Eliſha</hi> led them to <hi>Samaria,</hi> where they were taken. And <hi>Eliſha</hi> that travelled thus continually in the work of the Lord, was no Vagabond, nor Idle, Diſorderly perſon. And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> that walked three yeers naked and barefoot, for a ſign of what ſhould come upon <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. <hi>20.</hi> chap.</note> was no Vagabond, nor Idle, Diſorderly perſon. And <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> who was ſtayed in the Gate of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> as he was going from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> into the Land of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> yet he was no <hi>Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond</hi> nor <hi>Fugitive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. <hi>37.</hi> chap.</note> nor <hi>idle, diſorderly</hi> perſon. Nor <hi>Ionah</hi> the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> who at the <hi>Command</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> went out of his own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to <hi>Nineveh, to preach yet forty dayes, and Nineveh ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</hi> Neither was <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> nor any other of the Prophets (who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117937:11"/> obeyed the <hi>command</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> in declaring his <hi>Meſſages,</hi> and crying out againſt the filthy <hi>Abominations</hi> that was committed, both by <hi>Kings, Princes, Rulers, Iudges, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>People</hi>) any <hi>vagabonds,</hi> or <hi>idle, diſorderly</hi> perſons. Neither was <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.2.</note> who went into the <hi>wilderneſs</hi> of <hi>Judea,</hi> into all the countrey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Jordan, Preaching the Baptiſm of Repentance for the Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> he was no <hi>vagabond,</hi> nor <hi>idle, diſorderly</hi> perſon. And <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who went from <hi>Galilee</hi> to <hi>Jordan,</hi> to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized of <hi>John,</hi> and was afterward led by the <hi>Spirit</hi> into the <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and leaving <hi>Nazareth</hi> he came to <hi>Capernaum,</hi> which is upon the <hi>Sea coaſts,</hi> to dwel there, that it might be fulfilled which was ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Iſajah: From that time Ieſus began to preach and he walked by the Sea of Galilee, and he went all about Galilee tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in their Synagogues, and great multitudes of people followed him from</hi> Galilee, <hi>and from</hi> Decapolis, <hi>and from</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and from</hi> Judea, <hi>and from beyond</hi> Jordan, <hi>and he went up into a Mountain and taught them, and when he was come down from the Mount, he entered into Capernaum, and went into</hi> Peters <hi>houſe: and afterwards he went into a ſhip, and over the ſea, into the Countrey of the</hi> Gadarenes, <hi>and when the whole city that went out to meet him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 8.34.</note> 
               <hi>and when they ſaw him they beſought him to depart out of their coaſts, and he entred into a ſhip, and paſſed over into his own countrey, and he went about all the cities and villages, teaching in their Synagogues, and preaching, and healing every ſickneſs and every diſeaſe, and he called the twelve diſciples, and ſent them forth with power againſt unclean ſpirits; and they went forth by two and two; and when he had made an end of commanding the twelve, he departed thence to teach and preach in their Cities; and he went to</hi> Samaria, <hi>and when there was a Feaſt of the Iews, he went up to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and he went unto the Mount of Olives, and into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, and into many other places,</hi> not a few, <hi>and when he had finiſhed his travells, at laſt he went with his diſciples over the Brook Chedron, where was a garden, into which he and his diſciples entred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn <hi>18</hi> chap:</note> 
               <hi>where he and his diſciples had often reſorted, and there it was that</hi> Iudas <hi>betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him.</hi> And the Son of God, that travelled thus from city to city, and from countrey to countrey, and from one village to another, and had no where to lay his head; for he had left his natural pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents with whom he might have had an outward habitation, and a certain Dwelling place; but ſaid Chriſt, <hi>Lo it is written in the volume of thy Book,</hi> I <hi>come to do thy will O God;</hi> therefore he left his naturall Parents, to do the will of his heavenly Father: <hi>who had anointed him to preach good tydings to the meek,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. <hi>61</hi> chap.</note> 
               <hi>to binde up the broken hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captive, and the opening the priſon doores to them that are bound, to proclaim the acceptable yeer of the Lord, and the day of vengeance of our God, and to comfort all that</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117937:12"/> mourn, and to open the eyes of the blinde, to unſtop the deaf ears, to make the lame walk, and to raiſe the dead, and caſt out Devils, and to deſtroy the works of the Devill: And the Son of God that went thus about, continually doing good, at the will of his father, and had no certain dwelling-place, nor no where to lay his head, he was no Vagabond, nor Idol-diſorderly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt Jeſus ſent forth Labourers into his Fathers Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, to gather in the harveſt, and his Diſciples and Apoſtles which he ſent forth, they denyed themſelves, took up the Croſs, and forſook Father, Mother, Wife and Children, Brothers, Siſters, Houſes and Lands, and all that they had for their certain outward beings for their bodies, to follow Chriſt Jeſus, who had no where to lay his head, and to go whetherſoever he ſent them, to preach the Kingdome of heaven, and they went out by two and two, from City to City, preaching the Kingdome of heaven, and healing the ſick, and after his aſcenſion he gave them power to bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him in Jeruſalem, and in all Judea, and in Samaria, and unto the utmoſt part of the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8.</note> and they went abroad, ſee their travels therein, and the witneſs that they bore at Jeruſalem and other places; and <hi>Paul</hi> after his converſion, went into <hi>Arabia,</hi> and returned again into <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and after three years he went to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where he ſtayed fifteen days, and afterwards went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Regions of Aſſyria, and Cylicia, then had the Churches peace throughout all Judea, Galilee and Samaria, and were ede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and walked in the fear of God, and in the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt were multiplied; and Peter paſſed thorowout all quarters, and went to Lydda and Joppa, by the Sea-ſide, and from thence to Ceſaria; and at the ſtoning of <hi>Stephen</hi> there aroſe perſecution, ſo that they that were ſcattered abroad, travelled as far as Phenice and Antioch, and Cyprus, preaching to none but the Jews; and <hi>Barnabas</hi> was ſent from Jeruſalem to Antioch, and he went to Tarſus to ſeek <hi>Saul,</hi> and he found him, and brought him to Antioch, (where the Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians, none are Chriſtians but Chriſts Diſciples) where they were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated for the work whereunto the Holy Ghoſt had called them; ſo they being ſent forth by the Holy Ghoſt, departed unto <hi>Selen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> and from thence they ſayled to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and when they were at <hi>Salamis,</hi> they preached the <hi>VVord of God</hi> to the Jews in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and they went thorow the Ile unto <hi>Paphos,</hi> and from thence they came to <hi>Perga</hi> in <hi>Pamphilia,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> departed from them to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but when they departed from <hi>Perga,</hi> they came to <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Piſidia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 13. i5.</note> and entered into the Synagogue on the Sabbath-Day, and ſate down, and after the reading of the Law,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117937:12"/> and the Prophets, the Rulers of the Synagogue ſent to them, ſaying, Ye men and Brethren, if ye have any Word of Exhortation for the People, ſay on; Then <hi>Paul</hi> ſtood up and beckned with his hand, and ſpoke: And the next Sabbath day, the whole City almoſt came together to hear the word of God; but the Jewes were filled with envy, and ſpeak againſt thoſe things which were ſpoken by Paul, contradicting and blaſpheming; then <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> waxed bold, and ſaid, It was neceſſary that the Word of God ſhould have been firſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to you; but ſeeing ye put it from you, and judge your ſelves unworthy of everlaſting life, loe, we turn to the Gentiles; and the Word of the Lord was publiſhed thorowout all the Region: But the Jews ſtirred up the honourable and devout women, and the chief men of the city, and raiſed perſecution againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and expelled them out of their coaſts, but they ſhooke off the duſt off their feet againſt them, and came to <hi>Iconium,</hi> and by reaſon of the perſecution that roſe againſt them after their long ſtaying there, and ſpeaking boldly in the Lord, and teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the Word of his Grace, they fled unto <hi>Liſtra,</hi> and <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be,</hi> Cities of <hi>Lycaonia,</hi> and unto the Region that lyeth round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and went down to <hi>Attalia,</hi> and thence to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and paſſed through <hi>Phenice,</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and then were ſent back again to <hi>Antioch,</hi> where <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> continued teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and preaching the Word of the Lord; and after <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> parted, and <hi>Paul</hi> took <hi>Silas,</hi> and departed, and went thorow <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cylicia</hi> confirming the Churches, and afterward they went thorow <hi>Phrygia,</hi> and the Region of <hi>Galatia,</hi> and after to <hi>Myſia,</hi> and paſſing from <hi>Myſta,</hi> came down to <hi>Troas,</hi> and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from <hi>Troas,</hi> they went a ſtraight courſe to <hi>Samothracia,</hi> and the next day to <hi>Neapolis,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Philippi,</hi> which is the chief City of that part of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> where they abode certain dayes, and there they were whipt and put in priſon, and their feet made faſt in the ſtocks, and the Keeper of the Priſon was convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and came trembling, and fell down before <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and when they were let out of Priſon, they went into the houſe of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> and when they had ſeen the Brethren, they comforted them, and departed; and when they had paſſed thorow <hi>Amphipelis,</hi> and <hi>Apollonia,</hi> they came to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> as his manner was, went into the Synagogue of the Jews three Sabbath-dayes, and reaſoned with them out of the Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And from thence by night they went to <hi>Beria,</hi> where <hi>Silas</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> ſtayed, but <hi>Paul</hi> went to <hi>Athens,</hi> and departed from <hi>Athens</hi> and came to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> where he found a certain <hi>Iew,</hi> named <hi>Aquila,</hi> with his wife, <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> who were Tent-makers, and <hi>Paul</hi> abode with them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117937:13"/> and wrought, he being of the ſame Craft, and he reaſoned with the Iews in the Synagogues every Sabbath-day, perſwading the Iews and the Greeks; and when <hi>Silas</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> were come to him from <hi>Macedonia, Paul</hi> was preſſed in ſpirit, and teſtified to the Iews, that Ieſus was Chriſt: but they oppoſed and blaſphemed, and then <hi>Paul</hi> ſhook his raiment, and ſaid unto them, Your bloud be upon your own heads, I am clean, from henceforth I will go unto the Gentiles; and from <hi>Corinth</hi> he ſayled thence with <hi>Aquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> into <hi>Syria,</hi> and he came to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and he ſayled from <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and landed at <hi>Ceſaria,</hi> and ſo went down to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and after he had ſpent ſome time there, he went over all the countrey of Galatia, and Phrygia, and ſo thorow the countrey to viſit the Churches, and ſtrengthen the Brethren, till he came to Ieruſalem, where of the Brethren he was received gladly, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving purified himſelf, he entred into the Temple, to ſignifie the accompliſhment of the dayes of purification; and when the Iews of <hi>Aſia</hi> ſaw him there, they ſtirred up all the people, and laid hands on him, and ſet all Ieruſalem in an uproar, and ſo he was ſent to priſon into the Caſtle, and brought before the chief cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and after brought before a councel of the High Prieſt <hi>Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias,</hi> with Phariſees and Sadduces, and after he was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Feſtus,</hi> &amp; after that before King <hi>Agrippa</hi> and then was ſhipped away and ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> to appear before <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and at <hi>Rome</hi> he dwelt two yeers in his own hired houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 28.30, 31.</note> and received all that came to him, preaching the Kingdom of God, and teaching thoſe things which concern the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with all confidence, no man forbidding of him, &amp; he was injournying often in perills of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils by his own countrey-men, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the City, in perils in the Wilderneſs,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25 26, 27.</note> in perils in the Sea, in perils amongſt falſe brethren, in wearineſs and painfulneſs in watching often, in hunger and thirſt, in faſtings often, in cold and nakedneſs; and all theſe who had forſaken all, and travelled thus from city to city, and from countrey to countrey, labouring in the Vineyard and Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, were brethren, and fellow-labourers, and city-ſons of the new Jeruſalem, and were no Vagabonds, nor Idle; Diſorderly perſons; but bad the ſame perſons of the Prophets and Apoſtles, or any of them been here on earth at this day, and ſhould have wandered about here in England, from city to city, through towns and villages, they would have been counted va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds, and idle, diſorderly perſons, by this generation that is now living, who would have laid hold on them, and hailed them before magiſtrates, which would have ſent them to priſons, ſtocks, Bridewel, and whipt them, as ſome of the magiſtrates in England
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117937:13"/> have done unto thoſe people which are in ſcorn called <hi>quakers,</hi> by the ſons of <hi>Hagar</hi> the Aegyptian; but thoſe people that are called quakers, and travel about from city to city, and thus perſecuted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.5. <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.7.10. &amp; 12. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.3. <hi>&amp;c. Luke</hi> 24.19.</note> are ſuch as have denied themſelves, and forſaken all, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt did, and have taken up the ſame Croſs, and have received of the ſame power, and are called and ſent forth by the ſame Jeſus Chriſt to Declare the meſſage of God, that he is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all; and Declare the ſame Goſpel, and bear teſtimony of the ſame Jeſus Chriſt that the Prophets and Apoſtles did, and labour in the ſame Vineyard, and gather in of the ſame Wheat into the Garners, and by the ſame power do they cry out againſt the Prieſts and falſe Prophets, and falſe Worſhippers, and the Abominations that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted now, as ever was; and for this, and for no other, have they ſuffered, and do ſuffer all things by unreaſonable men, for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Captain of their ſalvation, and running the Race that he hath ſet before them, looking at Chriſt Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of their faith, and do rejoice that they are counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to ſuffer for his Names ſake; and were not that the Truth and Power of the Holy Ghoſt which they have received, by which they are carried forth with boldneſs to declare the truth, through much ſufferings, travels and labours in the Lords Vineyard, they ſhould not be thus perſecuted as they are; for as it was in the dayes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, (then the chief Prieſts and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees came to the Officers, whom they had ſent to take Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.45. <hi>&amp;c. Acts</hi> 28.22.</note> and ſaid, <hi>why have you not brought him?</hi> the Officers anſwered, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver man ſpeak like this man;</hi> then ſaid the Phariſees, <hi>Are ye alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived? have any of the Rulers or the Phariſees beleeved on him, but this people that are accurſed, who knoweth not the Law?</hi> And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the chief of the Jews ſaid to <hi>Paul, VVe know that this Sect is every where ſpoken against</hi>) ſo it is now here in <hi>England,</hi> all Sects and ſorts ſpeak againſt this one poor, low, deſpiſed thing, which is the Truth, which is owned, and received, and obeyed by thoſe People, which are in ſcorn called <hi>quakers,</hi> which is without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie that great myſtery of godlineſs that is hid from the wiſe and prudent of the World from all Generations, and is now at the Fathers pleaſure revealed unto Babes and Sucklings; For both <hi>Aepiſcopal,</hi> the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> the <hi>Independants,</hi> the <hi>Baptists, Seekers, Ranters, Papiſh,</hi> Profeſſor and prophane Prieſts, and People (and Rulers ſome) <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> all joyne together hand in hand againſt the <hi>Lord,</hi> and againſt his <hi>Anointed,</hi> unto whom he hath committed the Word of Reconciliation, and ſent abroad into the Miniſtry, who are by this generation impriſoned, whipped, ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſtoned, beaten, mocked, ſcoffed, ſcorned, derided, envied,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117937:14"/> and hated by all Sorts and Sects here in <hi>England,</hi> which ſits a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eaſe, and are in Peace, eating and drinking, and making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves merry, ſporting themſelves in the day time, heaping up Riches, clothing themſelves in coſtly Apparel and ſoft Raiment, living wantonly upon the earth, forgetting the rock from whence they are hewn, and ſo treaſuring up unto themſelves wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Day of Wrath and Revelation of the Judgement of God, which is to be revealed againſt all ungodlineſs and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe people that are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and that are thus uſed by this generation, have not been found begging at mens doors, neither have they been chargeable, or eaten any mans bread for nought, neither tranſgreſſed any Law of Equity, which is holy, righteous, juſt and good, therefore they are no Vagabonds, Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, nor Diſorderly, Idle perſons.</p>
            <p>But they are the Vagabonds who are gone out from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, <hi>(who is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all)</hi> and are fallen into the Tranſgreſſion, and are in envie and murder; theſe are in <hi>Cains</hi> nature, who are wrath, and their countenances falne, their Offering is not of God accepted, but their ſin lieth at their doore; theſe are drove into the earth, and have their habitation in the earth, and hide themſelves from the face of God, whom they ſee not, nor his voice hear, for in the earth they live, and have no habitation with God, for out from his preſence they are gone; ſuch are the Vagabonds and the Fugitives in the earth, from which they are accurſed, and it ſhall not henceforth yeeld unto them its ſtrength; <hi>Eſau</hi> was prophane, and hunting abroad and was a Reprobate, whoſe mind is turned from the Light, Chriſt Jeſus, is reprobated from God, and in him has no dwelling: <hi>Eſau</hi> was a cunning Hunter, and lived in the fields, and deſpiſed his birth-right; and all thoſe whoſe mindes are abroad ſeeking after honour, and following after pleaſures, living idlely upon the earth, are cunning Hunters, whoſe mindes are reprobated from Chriſt Jeſus, dwelling in the fields, deſpiſing their birth-right, theſe are Goats (and not Sheep) clothed with rough gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the firſt born, friends of the world, enemies to God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, fierce, envious, raſh, haters of good, perſecutors of the righteous ſeed, fornicators, as <hi>Eſau</hi> was, and hated of God, and could finde no place for repentance, theſe who are gone from the preſence of God, and turned from the Light, which they hate, becauſe their deeds are evill, and it reproves them; and although they have great habitations in the earth, and have compaſſed much of the earth into themſelves, and dwel therein, (and have no habitation with God) yet they are the Vagabonds, the Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117937:14"/> the Reprobates, and the diſorderly, idle perſons, which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſword is to be laid upon, and the Law is for, for they ſerve not the Lord but their own bellies; theſe are ſeen and known by the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light, which Light is the condemnation of all thoſe who walk contrary to it, and hate it. So likewiſe you may ſee here as followeth, who the unruly and diſorderly perſons be. There came to the city of <hi>Sodome</hi> two Angels at the even, and <hi>Lot</hi> ſate in the Gate of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and ſeeing them, he roſe up to meet them, and he preſſed upon them greatly, and they entred into his houſe, and he ſaid, <hi>Tarry all night and waſh your feet,</hi> and he did bake unleave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bread, and made them a Feaſt, and they did eat, and he ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>19.</hi> cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall riſe early and go on your wayes:</hi> but before they lay down, the men of the city, even the men of <hi>Sodome,</hi> compaſſed the houſe round, both old and young, all the people from every quarter, and they called unto <hi>Lot,</hi> and ſaid unto him, <hi>VVhere are the men which came in to thee this night? bring them out unto us;</hi> and they ſaid unto <hi>Lot, VVe will deale worſe with thee then with them;</hi> and they preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſore upon the man, even <hi>Lot,</hi> and came near to break the Door. Now unto you all, Judges, Mayors of Cities, Juſtices, Sheriffs, and Conſtables, I appeal to that of God in all your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, which bears me witneſs, who was the unruly and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly perſons, who was the cauſe of this riſing and tumult making in the city of <hi>Sodome?</hi> was juſt <hi>Lot</hi> and the two Angels, or the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites? (Iſay the Sodomites)</hi> But would not you have done unto the two Angels, as many of you have done unto thoſe people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>quakers,</hi> that when two of them have been come to a city, and have been entertained into a friends houſe, and there have peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſet together in the worſhip of God, and when the people of the city have known of it, have (juſt like the <hi>Sodomites</hi>) both old and young, have gathered together and beſet the houſe round and preſſed upon the doore, and broke the Windows, and made a great tumult, and have abaſed the people that have been as peaceable as <hi>Lot</hi> and the two Angels, but they have been charged with making the Tumult, and counted Diſorderly, and ſent to Priſon, and there kept, and the Diſorderly and the Unruly ſet free.</p>
            <p>And again, when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were come to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and preached that Chriſt had ſuffered, and riſen again from the dead, and that this Jeſus, ſaid <hi>Paul,</hi> whom I preach unto you, is Chriſt; and the devout <hi>Greeks,</hi> a great multitude, and of the chief Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, not a few, beleeved and conſorted with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas;</hi> but the <hi>Iews</hi> which beleeved not, moved with envie, took unto them certain lewde fellows of the baſer ſort, and gathered a company, and ſet all the city in an uproar, and aſſaulted the houſe of <hi>Iaſon,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:117937:15"/> and ſought to bring them out to the people,<note place="margin">Read Acts <hi>17.</hi> chap. to the <hi>10.</hi> verſe.</note> and when they found them not, they drew <hi>Iaſon,</hi> and certain of the brethren, whom <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> had received into his houſe, unto the Rulers of the City, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Theſe that have turned the world upſide down, are come hither alſo, and theſe all do contrary to the Decree of Ceſar, ſaying there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother King, one Jeſus.</hi> Now ſeeing the thing is ſo plain here before you, that it was the unbeleeving <hi>Iews,</hi> and the certain lewd fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of the baſer ſort that ſet all the City in an uproar, I wil ask this queſtion, <hi>VVhether the unbelieving Iews, with the certain lewde fellows of the baſer ſort, ought not to have given ſecurity to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and to have anſwered for ſetting the City in an uproar, yea, or nay? And whether</hi> Jaſon <hi>and his brethren, who were peaceable in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houſe together, ought not to have been ſet at liberty without giving ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, yea, or nay? Secondly, VVhetheer that were not a piece of inju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice done by the Rulers, who took ſecurity of</hi> Jaſon, <hi>and the others with him, and let the others, that made the uproare, go unpuniſhed, yea, or nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, <hi>VVhen</hi> Paul <hi>was come to Ieruſalem, and had purified himſelf, he went into the temple, to ſignifie the accompliſhment of the days of purification, and when the Jews which were of Aſia, ſaw</hi> Paul <hi>in the Temple, they ſtirred up all the people, and laid hands on</hi> Paul, <hi>crying out, Men of Iſrael help, this is the man that teacheth all men every where, againſt the People, and againſt the Law, and this place,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And all the City was moved, and the people ran together, and they took</hi> Paul <hi>and drew him out of the Temple, and ſhut the doors, and as they went about to kill him, tyding was brought to the chief Captain of the Band, that all Jeruſalem was in an uproare. I now appeal to all men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, who was it that ſet Jeruſalem in an uproare? was it</hi> Paul, <hi>that ſtood in the Temple, or was it the Jews of Aſia, who ſtirred up the people? I ſay it was the Jews of Aſia that ſtirred up the people and made the uproare, and not Paul: Then ought not the Jews of Aſia to have been bound with Chains for making the uproare, and to have been examined by ſcourging, and ſent to Priſon for going about to kill</hi> Paul, <hi>yea or nay? and ought not</hi> Paul <hi>the Apoſtle of Ieſus Christ to have been protected and ſet at liberty, that he might have gone on in the work of the Miniſtry, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So likewiſe the people called <hi>quakers,</hi> who at the <hi>Command</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> have gone, one or two at the moſt, into ſome high place which is commonly called the Church, without multitude or tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, and there have ſtood peaceably, and as they have been mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſo have ſpoke to the people, more or leſs, as utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance had been given them, ſome has not ſpoken before all has been done, but ſtraightway the people of the <hi>City</hi> or the <hi>Town,</hi> who have been gathered together in the high place that day, have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117937:15"/> by the prieſts means, riſe all up in a tumultuous manner, and have ſet the city or town in an uproar, juſt like the Jews of <hi>Aſia,</hi> beating and hawling the man or woman that has come in and ſpoke, and ſtraightway had them before the Mayor or Juſtice, who have ſent the innocent to Priſon, Bridewel, Stocks, or whipt and ſent them away with Paſſes, and they that have been the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill doers by making the Tumult, have been ſet free; and juſt as <hi>Paul</hi> was commanded to be bound with chains, and to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſcourging, and kept in priſon, and ſent from place to place till he came to <hi>Rome:</hi> So have the people called <hi>quakers</hi> been ſent to priſon by ſome of the Mayors and Juſtices in England, and there they have had Fetters of Iron hung upon their Legs, and kept cloſe Priſoners, their friends not ſuffered to come at them, and have laine there from Sizes to Sizes, and from Seſſions to Seſſions, before they have been ſet at liberty.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>AND now to you Judges, Mayors, Juſtices, Sheriffs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, who have done all theſe things to thoſe innocent harmleſs people and Servants of the moſt High God, that are ſcornfully called <hi>quakers,</hi> it is in love to your ſouls that I write thus unto you: And to that of God in every one of your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do I appeal, which bears me witneſs, Whoſe example have you followed in doing that to them which you have done? have you followed the example of Chriſt, who came to proclaim liberty to the Captives, and the opening of the priſon doors to them that are bound? or did you follow the example of <hi>Pharoah</hi> King of Aegypt, who kept Iſrael in bonds, and laid heavy burthens upon them? Have you followed the example of meek <hi>Moſes,</hi> who ſaid, I <hi>would to God all the Lords people were Prophets?</hi> Or did you not follow the example of <hi>Annas</hi> the high Prieſt, <hi>Caiaphas, John</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> and as many as were of the Kindred of the High Prieſts, Ru ers, Elders and Scribes,<note place="margin">Read Acts <hi>7.</hi> chap.</note> who commanded <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to preach no more in the Name of Jeſus? Do you follow the example of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithful, who received the Meſſengers of God and gave them meat, and when they roſe up he went with them to bring them on their way? Or do you not follow the example of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who ſaid (of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cah</hi> the Prophet of the Lord) <hi>Take this fellow and put him in priſon, and ſeed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction?</hi> Do you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the example of juſt <hi>Lot,</hi> who intreated the angels to go into his houſe, and made them a feaſt, and baked for them unleavened bread? Or do you not follow the example of <hi>Aſa,</hi> who was wrath
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117937:16"/> with <hi>Hanani</hi> the Seer, and in his rage ſent him to Priſon? Have you followed the example of the widow Woman of <hi>Zarepheth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">i <hi>King.</hi> i3. &amp; i7. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </note> who had but a handfull of Meale in a Barrel, and a little Oyle in a Cruſe for her ſelf and her ſon in the time of draught, yet at the Word of the Lord, ſpoken to her by <hi>Elijah,</hi> ſhe did make for <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> a Cake firſt, and afterwards for her ſon and her ſelf, and took the Prophet into her houſe, and they did eat many dayes, and he did dwell there, and the woman ſaid, I know that thou art a man of God, and that the Word of the Lord is in thy mouth? Or have you followed the example of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> who put forth his hand from the altar, and ſaid, Lay hold on him, meaning the prophet of God, that came out of <hi>Iudah,</hi> by the Word of the Lord, to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel,</hi> and cryed out againſt the altar in <hi>Bethel,</hi> at the ſame time that the King ſtood by the altar, and was offering ſacrifice upon it? Or will you follow the example of a Woman that was of great eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in <hi>Shunem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 6. <hi>chap.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.4. &amp; 13 <hi>verſes.</hi>
                  </note> that on a time when <hi>Eliſha</hi> came to <hi>Shunem,</hi> ſhe conſtrained him to turn into her houſe to eat bread, and ſhe ſaid unto her husband, behold I know that this is an holy man of God, (that paſſeth by us continually) let us make him a little Chamber I pray thee, and let us ſet him there a bed, and a table, and a ſtoole, and a candleſtick, that he may turn in thither when he cometh to us: and it fell on a day that when he came thither; he lay there? Or will you follow the example of <hi>Iezebel,</hi> who ſaid of <hi>Elijah, So let the gods do to me, and more alſo, if I make not thy life as the life of one of them, by to morrow about this time:</hi> and <hi>Iezebel</hi> ſlew the prophets of the Lord? Have you followed the example of <hi>Ioſhua?</hi> Or do you follow the example of the uncircumciſed <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines</hi> who put <hi>Sampſon</hi> in priſon, and bound him with fetters of braſs? Have you followed the example of <hi>Gideon?</hi> Or do you follow the example of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> who at the requeſt of his princes <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the prophet of God was put in the dungeon? Have you followed the example of <hi>David,</hi> a man after Gods own heart, who received the meſſage of God by the prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> who ſaid to the King, <hi>Thou art the man?</hi> Or do you not follow the example of <hi>Herod the Tetrarch,</hi> who <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> told, <hi>it is not lawful for thee to have thy Brother Philips wife,</hi> he ſent him to priſon. Have you followed the example of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> who ſaid to the Prophet <hi>Iſajah, Good is the word of the Lord which thou haſt ſpoken?</hi> Or do you not follow the example of <hi>Herod</hi> the King, who when he had killed <hi>James</hi> with the Sword, and ſaw it pleaſed the <hi>Jews,</hi> he put <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle of Chriſt in priſon? and have not ſome of you put the <hi>quakers</hi> in priſon becauſe you ſaw it pleaſed the prieſts that take tithes, and preach for hire, and divine for money, gifts, and rewards? Do you follow the example of <hi>Jehoſhaphat?</hi> Or have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117937:16"/> you not followed the example of the <hi>Roman</hi> Governours and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, who cauſed <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> to be whipt, and put in the Priſon, and to be kept ſafe, with their feet made faſt in the Stocks? Is the ſame minde in you which was in Chriſt Jeſus, who went alwayes about doing good? Or are you not in the ſame nature that the <hi>Babylonians</hi> and the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> were in, who caſt <hi>Shadrach, Meſhek,</hi> and <hi>Abednigo</hi> into the fiery Fornace, and <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Lyons Den? And ſeeing that ye have done ſo much as you have, Is there not the ſame minde in ſome of you as was in the bloudy <hi>Papiſts</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, to do as they did, if you had but a Law to put that in execution upon thoſe people that are called <hi>quakers,</hi> as they did by the <hi>Martyrs?</hi> And ſeeing that the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> put out <hi>Sampſons</hi> eyes, could not you and the Prieſts wiſh that the eyes of thoſe people, called <hi>quakers,</hi> were put out, that they might neither ſee to write more, nor to go about the land from City to City, and from one place to another, to cry out againſt the Prieſts and falſe Prophets, and the abominations of the Heathen, for the which they rage againſt the Truth, and them that do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>AND now unto all you both Magiſtrates and people, who have acted ſuch things as is before written, upon thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which are called <hi>quakers,</hi> To that of God in every one of your Conſciences, that bears me witneſs, do appeal; Are you all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as you call your ſelves, or have you acted like Chriſtians? The Diſciples of Chriſt were called Chriſtians: and they were Chriſtians indeed, who did no ſuch things as ye have done:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 11.26. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Phil</hi> 2.5. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>For I know, that if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature:</hi> and the ſame minde is in him as was in Chriſt Jeſus, and (in his meaſure) he is like Chriſt, holy, as he is holy, meek and lowly, dwelling in love and peace, doing to all men as he would be done unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: but I know the blaſphemy of them, that ſay they are Jews, and are not; and the blaſphemy of thoſe, that ſay they are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and are not, but are in the ſame nature that the <hi>Sodomites, Egyptians, Philiſtines, Babylonians, Idolaters,</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> were in, and are doing the ſame works, and committing the ſame abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that they committed, and yet you would be accounted Chriſtians, and think with your ſelves that you are good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. But ye are all made manifeſt and ſeen (with the Light,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16.</note> and by the Children of the Light) what you are, and what you all have done, and whom you alſo ſerve, for his Servants you are whom you obey. Whoſo committeth ſin, tranſgreſſeth alſo the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117937:17"/> Law,<note place="margin">i <hi>John</hi> 3.4.8. <hi>verſes.</hi>
                  </note> for ſin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law, which is holy, juſt, and good, and written in the heart; and he that committeth ſin is of the devill, for the Devil ſinneth from the beginning; For this purpoſe the Son of God was manifeſted, that he might deſtroy the Works of the Devil. Therefore while you have time prize it, and repent of the evill of your doings, and turn to the Lord God, who is gracious, merciful, and longſuffering, and patient in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, and hearken to the Word which is nigh you, in your heart and in your mouth, and obey his Commandments, <hi>Loving the Lord God with all your hearts, with all your ſouls, and your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as your ſelf,</hi> doing to all men as you would be done unto: Chriſt Jeſus is the Light of the World, learn of him, who is meek and lowly; <hi>He is the way, the truth and the life, and no man cometh to the Father but by him; and whoſo followeth him ſhall not walk in darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life;</hi> therefore if you wil be his Diſciples, (and Chriſtians) <hi>deny your ſelves, take up the Croſs, and follow him, that you may have life, for to as many as receive him, and beleeve on his Name, to them he gives power to become the Sons of God, and the Sons of God are led by the Spirit of God, into all Truth and Righteouſneſs.</hi> Therefore let the Spirit of God guide you, to run with cheerfulneſs the Race that Chriſt hath ſet before you, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſhame, counting it greater Riches to ſuffer afflictions with the children of God, rather then to injoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon. Therefore let every one that nameth the Name of JESUS, depart from iniquity, and take not the Name of God in vaine, <hi>For the feare of the Lord is the beginning of VViſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. i0, ii, i2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.21, 22 <hi>&amp; chap.</hi> 23.6, 7, 8. <hi>Dulc.</hi> 24.17. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6, 7.</note>Therefore you Judges, Juſtices, and Rulers all, be ye warned of doing any injuſtice, and take heed of vexing, oppreſſing, or perverting the Judgement of the Stranger, or Widow, or Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, or perverting the words of the Righteous, <hi>For he that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God:</hi> And ye that judge, take heed what you do, for ye are not to judge for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in judgement, therefore take heed and do it, for he hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, and what the Lord doth require of thee, even to do juſtly, and to love mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and to walk humbly with God: Wherefore, now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed and do it, For there is no iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the Law is not made for a righteous man, but for the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the unruly, and diſobedient, for the ungodly, and for ſinners, for the unholy and prophane, for murderers, whoremongers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, drunkards, curſers, ſwearers, lyars, perjured perſons, or any other thing that is contrary to the Law,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.11.</note> which is h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, juſt,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117937:17"/> pure and good. Therefore let him that ruleth rule with diligence, and be not ſlothfull in buſineſs, but fervent in ſpirit, ſerving the Lord; for Rulers ought to be a terrour to the evil doers, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to them that do wel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4, 5.</note> and in ſo doing he is the Miniſter of God to them that do good, and to them that do evill ſhall him fear, and in ſo doing, he that ruleth, beareth not the Sword in vain, but he that doth contrary hereunto, beareth the Sword in vain, and to an account will the Lord God call him, (for his ſo ruling and doing unjuſtly, and for bearing the Sword in vain) who is coming to judge the ſecrets of all mens hearts, who ſhall give an account in that day before the Judgement ſeat of Chriſt, where all men muſt appear, that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or evill; <hi>For the ſame meaſure that ye have mete to others, will the Lord mete to you again with juſtice, for not one ſin ſhall go unpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed.</hi> Knowing therefore the terrors of the Lord, I perſwade you, and he that hath an eye to ſee, let him ſee, and an ear to hear, let him hear, and an heart to underſtand, let him conſider, here is ſet before you the good works, and the evil doers, that Rulers ought to be a terror to, and a protection to them that do wel.</p>
               <p>But it maybe you will object, and ſay, <hi>That thoſe men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that are called quakers (which goes about preaching, are evill doers,</hi> viz. <hi>ſowers of ſedition, and preachers of new Doctrine, and ſuch as creep into houſes, and lead ſilly women captive, and that they are a people of uncivill behaviour towards their ſuperiors and bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, and therefore they are not to be protected, but puniſhed as evill doers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That thoſe who have been alwayes perſecutors of the righteous, and enemies to the Truth, have in all ages in their rage, counted the Servants of God to be evil doers, ſowers of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and preachers of new Doctrine; for ſo <hi>Haman</hi> he was wrath and full of indignation with <hi>Mordecai,</hi> becauſe <hi>Mordecai</hi> did not reverence him, and <hi>Haman</hi> ſaid likewiſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſth.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 5 <hi>chap</hi>
                  </note> All this (meaning his honour) availeth me nothing, ſo long as I ſee <hi>Mordecai</hi> the Jew, ſitting in the Kings gate, who would not riſe up and bow to him, although it was the Kings Command ſo to do: And <hi>Haman</hi> ſaid of the reſt of the Iews, that their laws were divers from all people, neither, ſaid he, do they keep the Kings Laws, therefore ſaid <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to the King, It is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them, but if it pleaſe the King, ſaid <hi>Haman,</hi> let it be written that they may be deſtroyed, and I wil pay ten thouſand talents into the hands of thoſe that ſhall have the charge of the buſineſs, to bring it into the Kings Treaſuries. And ſo likewiſe the unbelieving Iews which were of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſaid of <hi>Paul,</hi> in his time, Away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, for it is not fit that he ſhould live.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 22.22.</note> And the Iews
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117937:18"/> of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> who were moved with envie, ſaid unto the Rulers of the City, of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as,</hi> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e have turned the world up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide-down; and ſaid of <hi>Iaſon,</hi> and the Brethren, and <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> that theſe all do contrary to the Decrees of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> ſaying that there is another King, one JESUS. And when <hi>Paul</hi> was at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> diſputing in the Synagogue with the <hi>Iews,</hi> and in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place dayly with them that met with him: he was counted by the Philoſohers, the Epicuranes, and Soicks, that encountred him, a Babler; a ſpeaker of new Doctrines, and one that ſeemed to be a ſetter up of ſtrange Gods, becauſe he preached unto them Jeſus, and the reſurrection:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Read Acts</hi> 17. <hi>chap. Acts</hi> 24.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> and likewiſe <hi>Annanias</hi> the High Prieſt, with the Elders, and <hi>Turtulus,</hi> the Orater ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Foelex,</hi> we have found this man a peſtilent Fellow, and a mover of Sedition among all the Jews throughout the world, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of the <hi>Nazarenes.</hi> And <hi>Mordicai, Paul, Silas,</hi> and <hi>Jaſon,</hi> with the Brethren, were no evill doers, although they were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd as for thoſe people which are called Quakers, that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel throughout <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and other places, and go through Towns and Villages, from City to City, they are faithful, painful labourers in the Lords Vineyard, and are not of that ſort which creep into houſes, and lead captive ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women, laden with ſin, and led aſide with divers luſts, but it is the Prieſts of the nations, that preach for Tithes, Hire, Gifts and Rewards, (and others) that have got not only, (a form) but many forms of godlineſs, but the Power of Godlineſs they have not, for thoſe that have the true Power of Godlineſs they deny and perſecute: I ſay, that (the Steeplehouſes which are builded up with Stone, Lime, Brick, Wood, Iron, Lead, and Glaſs, which are commonly called Churches, and into other houſes) the Prieſts (and others) creep into, and it is they that lead thoſe people cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, who are ſilly men and women that there meet together, who are laden with ſin, <hi>viz.</hi> Curſing, Swearing, Lying, Envie, Wrath, Malice, Fighting, quarrelling, Mocking, Scoffing, Covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry, Oppreſſed, Cheating, Cozening, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Gluttony, Chambering, and Wantonneſs, Whoredome, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Pride and Fornication; and they are led away with divers Luſts, <hi>viz.</hi> The Luſts of the Fleſh, the Luſts of the Eye, and the Pride of Life,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.16, 17. <hi>mes</hi> 1.15.</note> and all the Faſhions and Cuſtomes in the World, which Luſts, when it conceiveth, bringeth forth Sin, and Sin, when it is finiſhed, bringeth forth Death. And theſe are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117937:18"/> that are ever learning of the Prieſts (and others) but are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver able to come to the knowledge of the Truth,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>chap. Tit.</hi> 1.10, 11.16.</note> by ſuch Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers who are diſcribed by <hi>Paul</hi> (a Miniſter of the Word) to be ſuch as are lovers of their own ſelves, covetous, proud boaſters, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, (ſaying they are Miniſters of Chriſt, but are not) tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſuch things, which they ought not, for filthy lucres ſake, ſubverting whole houſes, diſobedient to Parents, unthankful, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, unruly, vain-talkers, deceivers, truce-breakers, falſe-accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, incontinent, without natural affections, fierce deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, traiterous, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God, having a Form of Godlineſs, but denying the Power thereof: All people from ſuch turn away, for they reſiſt the Truth, and are men of corrupt mindes, Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate concerning the faith, of which you have been long hearing, and ever learning, and yet you are not come to the knowledge of the truth: Therefore while you have time prize it, for thoſe that are turned from ſuch Teachers, and are turned to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Light of the World, they are come to the Way,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.11. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14 6. <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20.27. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3, 4.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt, which is life eternall, <hi>For Chriſt is the VVay, the Truth, and the Life, and no man comes to the Father but by him,</hi> it is he that guides them continually and brings them to glory: the children of the Lord are not taught of man, but of the Lord, <hi>as many as are the Sons of God, are led by the ſpirit of God, and the ſpirit of God leads them into all truth, and the Vnction wherewith they are anointed, teaches them all things, ſo that they need not to be taught of men, for the Grace of God teaches them to deny all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly righteouſly, and holy, in all manner of converſation;</hi> and theſe that are thus taught, are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the true Church, which is built up of living Stones, Chriſt Jeſus being the chief corner Stone; and this is the houſe of God, not made with hands, but is a Spirituall Houſe, the Houſe of God, where God doth dwel and in it walk:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21, 22. <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.18.24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18, i9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23, 24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>This Church is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but in God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; and the Body of Chriſt is the Church, and is the Ground and Pillar of Truth, and the Members thereof are one Body, and Chriſt he is the Head of the Body; and they who are Members of this Church, are come to Mount Sion, and to the City of the living God, the Heavenly Ieruſalem, and to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of Angels, to the generall Aſſembly, and to the Church of the Firſt-born, which are written in Heaven; and to God the Iudge of all, and to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, and to Ieſus the Mediator of the New-Covenant, and to the blood of ſprinckling, which ſpeaketh better things then that of</hi> Abel. Therefore all people, high and low, rich and poor, bond and free, hearken unto Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Jeſus, hear ye him that your ſouls may live; he that hears the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117937:19"/> voice of the Son of God ſhall live;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.3.</note> ſee that ye refuſe not him that ſpeaketh, and hearken to the Word of the Lord, that is nigh you, in your hearts and in your mouths, to it incline your ear; Oh hear that your ſouls may live: and to day if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, for this is the wil of God, even your ſanctification.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7. <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. <hi>chap.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.24.</note> Therefore why will ye die, O people of England. Return, return unto the Lord God who is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all; for who is a God like our God, merciful, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, long-ſuffering, and abundant in Goodneſs and Truth, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin, he wil ſubdue iniquity, and will caſt ſin into the depth of the ſea, and he wil perform the Truth unto <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11.</note> and the Mercy to <hi>Abraham,</hi> which he hath ſworn unto our Fathers from the dayes of old: He is a faithful God, and all his Promiſes are; Yea, and Amen. <hi>He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith;</hi> and he that wil be filthy, let him be filthy ſtil.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="queries">
               <head>Here followeth ſome <hi>QUERIES</hi> to be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any of thoſe who are called by men Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that preach in the High Places, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that plead for, and uphold them.</head>
               <p>Quaery 1. WHether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that makes Bargains with the People of a Pariſh to have 100 l. a Yeer (more or leſs) for their preaching, and take Bond of the People for the payment of the ſame, ſeeing that Chriſt ſaid to his Miniſters, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give;</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Flock of Chriſt is to be fed willingly, and not for filthy lucre ſake,</hi> yea or nay? <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt, that Preach for Hire, and Divine for Mony, yea or nay? <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that ſeek for gain from their quarter, like greedy dogs, which think they can never have enough, yea or nay? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.25.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that feed themſelves with the Fat, and clothe themſelves with the Wool, and care not for the Flock, but let it become a prey? Read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. chap.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that take Tithes for their preaching, ſeeing that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood changed, and the Law diſanulled by which Tithes was paid, yea or nay? Read <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. chap.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117937:19"/>6 Whether thoſe be miniſters of Chriſt that ſue men at Law for Tithes, ſeeing that the Prophet of God cryed out againſt them that prepared war againſt thoſe that put not into their mouths, yea or nay? <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="7">7 What that Hire is that Chriſt ſaid the Labourer is worthy of, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.7, 8. and whether that be not an unrighteous thing of a man, that demands wages of men, and compels them to pay him wages who never ſet him to work, nor he never wrought for them, yea or nay. Read <hi>Luke</hi> 10. chap. to the 15 verſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether it is the work of the Miniſters of Chriſt, to ſtay at home to bury the dead, or to go into all nations and preach the Goſpel, according to Chriſts command, yea or nay. <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.59, 60.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether the Prophets or Apoſtles of Chriſt uſed to obſerve the Statutes of <hi>Omri,</hi> or to take delight in the works of <hi>Ahab,</hi> or to walk in their Councels, yea or nay. <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.16. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 16. chap.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Whether thoſe be miniſters of Chriſt whoſe god is their belly, whoſe glory is their ſhame, who minde earthly things, yea or nay. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that go in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for Honour and Rewards, and follow their own pernicious wayes, and through covetouſneſs, with feigned words, make merchandiſe of ſouls, yea or nay. <hi>Iude</hi> 11. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>chap. Rev.</hi> 18. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether thoſe be Miniſters that puts money to uſury, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſaid, he neither lent on Uſury, nor men lent me on Uſury, yea or nay. Read <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that will ſit and eat and drink with the Drunkards, and ſmite his fellow-ſervants, yea or nay. <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.49.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that are called of men Maſter, and deſire to walk in long Robes, and love the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt Rooms at feaſts, and greetings in the Market place, and have the higheſt ſeats in thoſe places which are called churches, and there ſtand praying, and for a pretence make long prayers, and devour widows houſes, yea or nay. Read <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. chap. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.46. &amp; 18.10, 11.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt which the Lord ſaith he is againſt, who ſteal his Word from their Neighbour, and uſe their tongues, and ſay, The Lord ſaith, when he ſpake not to them, and run when he ſent them not, and come when he called them not, yea or nay. Read <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. chap.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Whether thoſe be Miniſters of Chriſt that preach up out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117937:20"/> Temples made with hands, and in them uphold an outward bodily worſhip, which profiteth little, ſeeing that <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame, and <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſtoned to death for witneſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them likewiſe; and Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, <hi>that God is a ſpirit, and they true worſhippers that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in spirit and in truth,</hi> yea or nay. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Acts</hi> 7. <hi>chap.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18.</p>
               <p n="17">17. That when a company are gathered together (of <hi>Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, Swearers, Lyars, VVhores,</hi> and <hi>VVhoremongers, Adulterers, Fornicators, Thieves, Murderers, Scoffers, Scorners, Covetous, Proud Heady, High minded people, Lovers of Pleaſures more then lovers of God, Prophane, carnall, earthly minded people, dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, having their underſtandings darkned, ſuch as are aliens and ſtrangers from the life and Covenant of Grace</hi>) and all theſe ſit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the High Place, commonly called the church, and ſing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 2, <hi>And heale me Lord, for why, thou knoweſt my bones do quake for fear.</hi> I ſay, is any of thoſe perſons, above mentioned, in that condition that <hi>David</hi> was in, when he ſaid, I <hi>am weak, O Lord heal me, for my bones are vexed;</hi> or in that condition that <hi>Moſes</hi> was in, when he ſaid, <hi>I exceedingly fear and quake,</hi> yea or nay. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.21.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Whether ſuch perſons above mentioned, that ſing, <hi>All the night long</hi> I <hi>waſh my bed with tears of my complaints,</hi> and yet never witneſſed that condition that <hi>David</hi> was in, when he ſaid, <hi>All the night</hi> I <hi>make my bed to ſwim,</hi> I <hi>water my couch with tears:</hi> I ſay, do not ſuch perſons lye, and turn the Scriptures into a lye, and ſo blaſpheme the Name of God, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Whether ſuch perſons above mentioned, that makes Songs of the Saints conditions declared of in the Scripture, which was never none of their own, do not they lye, and tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Scripture into a lye, and ſo blaſpheme the Name of God, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Did Chriſt Jeſus or his Apoſtles at any time teach ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons above mentioned to turn <hi>Davids</hi> Prayers, the confeſſion of his Sins, his Sorrows, his Afflictons, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad complaints he made thereof, and the Enemies of the <hi>Church,</hi> his Exhortations his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, and other Scriptures, into Rime and Meeter, and to ſing them as Songs, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="21">2i. Whether thoſe men who are called Miniſters, that teach the people ſo to ſing, and thoſe people that do ſo ſing, do not make <hi>David</hi> to become the Song of Drunkards now in theſe dayes, as he was in thoſe dayes that he was King, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Whether ſuch ſinging by ſuch perſons as is here above ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, be a Teaching and Admoniſhing one another in Pſalms and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:117937:20"/>23. Whether ſuch perſons above mentioned that ſo ſing, ſing with the Spirit, and ſing with underſtanding, and ſing with grace in their hearts unto the Lord, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Whether the praiſes of the wicked be not as abominable to the Lord as their prayers, yea or nay.</p>
               <p n="25">25. Whether thoſe that thus walk in darkneſs, and lead the blinde thus out of their way, be not blinde guides, and lie under the curſe of God for their ſo doing, yea or nay. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.18.</p>
               <p n="26">26. Whether thoſe perſons that are called of men Miniſters, and Teachers, and profeſs themſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and yet do ſuch things as is before expreſſed, be not ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to Chriſt and his Miniſters, and ſo fit to be caſt out, yea or nay. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 34.10.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Whether the two Poets <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins,</hi> with others, who turned the Pſalms and other Scriptures into Rhime and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, did do it by the Spirit of God, or by the wiſdom of faln man, ſeeing that no propheſie of the Scriptures are of any private inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, yea or nay.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Theſe queries are written and ſent forth by me, who am known by the name of Henry Clark.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="copyright_statement">
            <p>This is entred according to Order.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
